A Guide to the Centreville, Virginia Collection, 1840-1977
Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library
The Centreville, Virginia Collection, 1840-1977
Fairfax County Public Library
MSS 03-04
0.5 linear feet
The Centreville, Virginia Collections consists of 0.5 linear feet, spans the years 1840-1977, and contains historical papers, reports, lecture notes, a hand-drawn land survey, a broadside, manuscript drafts, and a photocopied map.
Virginia Room staff
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None
Acquisition Information
Collection assembled by Virginia Room staff over a period of years. 1874 and 1877 tax receipts gift of Keith Pearson.
Historical and Biographical Information
In 1792, an act of the Virginia General Assembly incorporated the Town of Centerville (later to be renamed Centreville). The area, originally known as the village of Newgate, consisted primarily of tobacco land owned by the Carrs, Newtons, Jetts, and Lanes as well as two local landmarks: the Newgate Tavern and Mount Gilead.
Not long after the town’s incorporation, the area saw a rise in the establishment of mills and tanneries, but the village entered a long period of gradual decline. Its deterioration was furthered by the Civil War, of which Centreville became a hotbed of activity. The town was strategically important due to its high elevation and close proximately to turnpikes, railroads, and Washington, D.C. Both the Confederate and Union armies occupied the heavily fortified town throughout the war. In 1862, the Confederate army constructed a 5.5 mile track known as the Centreville Military Railroad, making it the first exclusively military railroad ever built.
The war left Centreville heavily scarred and it struggled to recover during the post-war era. The area remained largely stagnant until the 1980s which saw a dramatic population boom with the construction of housing developments and shopping centers. In 1986, Fairfax County established the Centreville Historic Overlay District which includes notable historical buildings such as Mount Gilead, St. John’s Episcopal Church, Harrison House, Havener House, Spindle Sears House, and the Old Stone Church.
Scope and Content
The Centreville, Virginia Collections consists of 0.5 linear feet, spans the years 1840-1977, and contains historical papers, reports, lecture notes, a hand-drawn land survey, a broadside, manuscript drafts, and a photocopied map. Included are documents relating to the history of Centreville, Virginia such as tax receipts for George W. Steel and his son-in-law David Pierson; reports on the discovery of the Willoughby Newton boundary stone; preliminary drafts for “The Three Lives of Walney” by Anne S. Beresford and “Walney” by Elizabeth Brown Pryor; and an 1840 hand-drawn survey of the division of John Carter’s Sudley plantation.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Centreville Grange No. 750 Dues Account Book, MSS 05-32
None
Index Terms
Beresford, Beatrice Anne (1922-1982); Carter, John (?-1838); Centreville (Va.) - History; Centreville United Methodist Church; Clarke, Susan Summers (1844-1939); Newton, Willoughby; Old Stone Church Centreville, Va.); Patterson, Rev. William; Pierson, David (1852-?); Pryor, Elizabeth Brown (1951-2015); Steel, George W. (1805-?); Sudley plantation; Turberville, Anne S. (1885-1965); Walney Farm (Centreville, Va.)
Container List
- Three talks about the history of Centreville, Virginia made by Anna S. Turberville, 1951, 1952, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Notes, Tour of Historic Landmarks of the Centreville Area, Conducted by Rev. William Patterson, St. John’s Church, 1966 October 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Briefing paper, Search for Willoughby Newton Boundary Stones. February 20-21, 1971, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Report, The Willoughby Newton Boundary Stone Discovery in Centreville, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Broadside, "Centreville United Methodist Church For Sale", Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Preliminary draft, “Walney” by Elizabeth Brown Pryor, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Preliminary draft, “The Three Lives of Walney” by Anne S. Beresford, 1977 April (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Obituary, Susan Summers Clarke (former resident of Level Green Farm), Merced Sun Star, 1939 February 3 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Tax receipts, George W. Steele and David Pierson, 1874, 1877 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Map, "Centreville, Va. Positions of Artillery" Sept 1861-Jan 1862 [photocopy], Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Survey, “Survey of Division of Sudley to part of the real estate left by John Carter, dec.”, 1840 June 5 (Folder Oversize)